<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<article>
	<title>Storing Trust Assertions in PKCS#11 Modules</title>

	<articleinfo>
		<releaseinfo>Rough "rougher than burlap underwear" draft</releaseinfo>
		<date>December 2010</date>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Stef</firstname>
				<surname>Walter</surname>
				<affiliation>
					<orgname>Collabora Ltd</orgname>
					<address>
						<email>stefw@collabora.co.uk</email>
					</address>
				</affiliation>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
	</articleinfo>

	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>

		<para>Trust assertions are represent bits of trust information used by an
			application in trust decisions. For example, trust assertions can represent
			certificate authority root anchors, pinned certificate exceptions, or
			revocation lists.</para>

		<para>PKCS#11 XXXREFXXX is a useful and widely supported standard for storage and use
			of keys and certificates. It is often used with smart cards.</para>

		<para>This specification outlines how to store and lookup trust assertions via the
			PKCS#11 API. We detail an extension which accomplishes this.</para>

		<para>XXX</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Trust Assertions</title>
		<para>A trust assertion describes a level of trust in a certain subject for a
			given purpose. Conceptually each trust assertion is a triple
			containing the following:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Reference to the Subject</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Purpose</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Level of Trust</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>We examine each of these parts of the triple in further detail below.</para>

		<section>
			<title>Level of Trust</title>

			<para>XXX</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Untrusted: Explicitly untrusted. Override other
					trust.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Trusted: Explicitly trusted. Override other
					trust</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Trust Anchor: Explicitly trusted anchor which
					can confer its trust (eg: via signatures) on other
					subjects.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Purpose</title>

			<para>A trust assertion refers to a specific purpose or usage. A
				certificate may be trusted for purposes like: email, code signing,
				authenticating a server.</para>

			<para>In addition to the usage, the purpose can contain a more specific
				designation, such as the hostname of a server.</para>
		</section>


		<section>
			<title>Subject Reference</title>
			<para>Each trust assertion contains a reference to the subject. This is the thing
				that is trusted. In this specification we will deal exclusively with
				certificates as the subject. However .</para>

			<para>There are two ways to refer to a certificate depending on whether
				that certificate is being referred to as a trust root (like a certificate
				authority) or referred to by another trusted certificate.</para>

			<para>Certificates used as trust roots are referred to by the complete DER
				encoding of the certificate.</para>

			<para>Certificates verified by another certificate (signed as part
				of a certificate chain) are referred to by the DER value of the issuer
				field and the serial number.</para>

			<para>Referring to a trust root certificate by its issuer and serial number
				is meaningless.</para>

			<para>Referring to a certificates signed by another certificate would preclude uses
				such as certificate revocation lists.</para>

			<para>Therefore different methods MUST be used to refer certificates in these
				different situations.</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>PKCS#11 Trust Assertion Objects</title>

		<para>Trust assertions are stored as objects on a PKCS#11 token. Although these are
			specific to a certificate, they do not need to be stored on the same token as
			the certificate.</para>

		<para>When represented as PKCS#11 objects, trust assertions get a bit less elegant
			than the reference + purpose + trust-level described above. This is done
			for practicality and minimizing the number of PKCS#11 lookups required
			to do an operation.</para>

		<section>
			<title>Common Trust Assertion Object Attributes</title>

			<para>First we describe the attributes that all trust assertion objects have in
				common. All trust assertions are of the class CKO_G_TRUST_ASSERTION.</para>

			<table>
				<title>General trust assertion attributes</title>
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Attribute</entry>
							<entry>Data Type</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_CLASS</entry>
							<entry>CK_OBJECT_CLASS</entry>
							<entry>CKO_G_TRUST_ASSERTION</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>CK_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>The type of trust assertion. This represents
								the trust level. See more details below.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_PURPOSE</entry>
							<entry>CK_UTF8_CHAR array</entry>
							<entry>The string representation of the purpose, usually
								an OID.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

			<para>The CKA_G_PURPOSE attribute contains a string which represents the purpose
				of the trust assertion. These are generally OIDs. The following predefined
				values match those of the Extended Key Usage X.509 extension. Other values
				may be used when interoperability of the trust assertion between multiple
				applications is not desired.</para>

			<table>
				<title>Predefined Purposes</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Value</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.1</entry>
							<entry>TLS Server Authentication</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.2</entry>
							<entry>TLS Client Authentication</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.3</entry>
							<entry>Code Signing</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.4</entry>
							<entry>Email Protection</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.5</entry>
							<entry>IPSec Endpoint</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.6</entry>
							<entry>IPSec Tunnel</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.7</entry>
							<entry>IPsec User</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.8</entry>
							<entry>Time Stamping</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

			<para>Each different type of trust assertion is represented by a different
				CK_G_TRUST_TYPE value. The following types are defined.</para>

			<table>
				<title>Trust assertion types</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Trust Type</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>CKT_G_CERTIFICATE_UNTRUSTED</entry>
							<entry>A trust assertion that represents an explicitly
								untrust in a certificate.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKT_G_CERTIFICATE_TRUST_EXCEPTION</entry>
							<entry>A trust assertion that represents an explicitly
								trust in a certificate.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKT_G_CERTIFICATE_TRUST_ANCHOR</entry>
							<entry>A trust assertion that represents a trust anchor
								which is used as the root of a certificate trust
								tree.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Certificate Exception Trust Assertion</title>

			<para>A certificate exception is a trust assertion which signifies a trusted level
				of trust in a certificate. The expectation is that all other trust validation
				is overridden by this trust.</para>

			<para>The certificate is referenced by a using the entire DER encoding of the
				certificate.</para>

			<para>All certificate exceptions have a designated peer as part of their purpose.
				In the case of TLS authentication purposes, this is the host name of the
				peer that is being communicated with. In the case of email protection
				purposes this is the email address this certificate is to be used with.</para>

			<para>In addition to the following, all the general trust assertion attributes
				are present on a certificate exception object.</para>

			<table>
				<title>Certificate Exception Attributes</title>
					<tgroup cols="3">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Attribute</entry>
							<entry>Data Type</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>CK_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>CKT_G_CERTIFICATE_TRUST_EXCEPTION</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_PEER</entry>
							<entry>CK_UTF8_CHAR array</entry>
							<entry>The peer part of the purpose.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_CERTIFICATE_VALUE</entry>
							<entry>Byte array</entry>
							<entry>The DER encoding of the certificate.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Certificate Anchor Trust Assertion</title>

			<para>A certificate anchor is a trust assertion which is to be used with a
				certificate authority that is a trust root authority to verify
				other certificates with.</para>

			<para>This type of object signifies a trust anchor level of trust.</para>

			<para>The certificate is referenced by a using the entire DER encoding of the
				certificate.</para>

			<para>In addition to the following, all the general trust assertion attributes
				are present on a certificate exception object.</para>

			<table>
				<title>Certificate Anchor Attributes</title>
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Attribute</entry>
							<entry>Data Type</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>CK_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>CKT_G_CERTIFICATE_TRUST_ANCHOR</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_CERTIFICATE_VALUE</entry>
							<entry>Byte array</entry>
							<entry>The DER encoding of the certificate.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Certificate Untrusted Assertion</title>

			<para>An untrusted certificate is a trust assertion which signifies the explicit
				lack of	trust in a certificate. An example of this is an item in a CRL
				or a certificate explicitly marked as untrusted by a user.</para>

			<para>The certificate is referenced by a using the issuer and serial number
				of the certificate in question.</para>

			<para>In addition to the following, all the general trust assertion attributes
				are present on a certificate exception object.</para>

			<table>
				<title>Untrusted Certificate Attributes</title>
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Attribute</entry>
							<entry>Data Type</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_G_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>CK_TRUST_TYPE</entry>
							<entry>CKT_G_CERTIFICATE_UNTRUSTED</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_ISSUER</entry>
							<entry>Byte array</entry>
							<entry>DER-encoding of the certificate issuer name</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>CKA_SERIAL_NUMBER</entry>
							<entry>Byte array</entry>
							<entry>DER-encoding of the certificate serial number</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Operations</title>

		<section>
			<title>Building a Certificate Chain</title>

			<para>During TLS or other certificate verification operations, a certificate chain
				must be built up. The certificate chain starts with a trust anchor and
				each certificate in the chain is signed by the previous one. The chain ends
				with the endpoint certificate for the peer.</para>

			<para>Conceptually building a certificate chain can be described as two operations
				1) building the chain based on trust assertions, and 2) allowing then
				allowing falsification of all or part of the chain based on trust
				assertions.</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Check if the endpoint certificate has a certificate exception
					for the given purpose (and peer). If a certificate exception is found
					then the certificate chain consists of one certificate and is considered
					valid at this point.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>Complete the initial certificate chain. Often the peer does not
					send a complete chain and only sends its own certificate. Build up the
					chain backwards from the bottom up using the certificate issuer to to
					perform PKCS#11 lookups for objects matching the CKA_ISSUER. This is
					done until a self-signed certificate is reached, or a certificate is not
					found.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>Look for a trust anchor for each certificate in the chain
					starting from the certificate that signed the endpoint certificate. When
					a trust anchor is found then the certificate chain is truncated at that
					point.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>Allow falsification for each certificate in the resulting
					certificate chain by checking whether each certificate has PKCS#11
					untrusted certificate trust assertion. If at any point an untrusted
					trust assertion is found (eg: CRL) then the certificate chain is
					considered invalid.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>Pass the resulting certificate chain to the crypto library for
					 further validation.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Justifications</title>

		<para>Some answers to this spec was designed as it is.</para>

		<section>
			<title>Why use a complete DER encoding?</title>
			<para>Conceivably we could use a hash of the certificate instead of the
				CKA_G_CERTIFICATE_VALUE. NSS Trust Objects XXREFXX uses hashes in this
				way.</para>

			<para>In the current climate of hash algorithms being broken in various ways
				it seems more prudent to avoid the hashing of the certificate and just
				use the complete certificate DER-encoding for lookups.</para>

		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Why lookup untrusted certificates by issuer + serial number?</title>

			<para>Certificate revocation lists XXREFXX do not generally contain the full value
				of the certificate or a hash thereof. They simply contain serial numbers,
				which when combined with the issuer of the certificate revocation list,
				are meant to uniquely identify a given certificate.</para>

			<para>In order to support CRLs exposed as untrusted assertions (one of the design
				goals) we must limit ourselves to this method of identifying untrusted
				certificates.</para>

		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Why not use NSS Trust Objects?</title>

			<para>NSS contains an implementation of storing trust information via PKCS#11.
				This has not been completely documented, but an overview is available
				here XXREFXX.</para>

			<para>After careful study of NSS's method of storing trust information, and discussion
				with others, the following inherent problems are apparent.</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandates the use of SHA1 and MD5 hashes both of which are
					cryptographically broken in some way XXREFXX. See above
					XXLINKXX</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>Only supports a distinct set of purposes, new purposes are
					not supported.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>Does not support a trust assertion limited to a single peer, which
					precludes storage of trust assertions.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</section>
	</section>

</article>
